Guide to the John A. Nietz Papers UA.90.F95
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John A. Nietz Papers
1800-1970
1931-1960
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Nietz, John A. (John Alfred)
UA.90.F95
18.55 Linear Feet (19 boxes)
John A. Nietz was a professor in the School of Education at the University of Pittsburgh from 1926 to his retirement in 1958 and was renowned for his collection of old school textbooks.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John A. Nietz in 1958.
Biography
John A. Nietz was a professor in the School of Education at the University of Pittsburgh from 1926 to his retirement in 1958 and was renowned for his research on the history of education and his collection of old school textbooks.
Nietz was born near Toledo, Ohio, in 1888. He earned an A.B. degree at Ohio Northern University in 1914, a M.A. at Ohio State University in 1919, and a Ph.D. in Education at the University of Chicago in 1933. During his stay at the University of Chicago, Nietz studied under the famous philosopher and educational theorist, John Dewey.
Nietz was married to Ruby K. Nietz, who died in 1953, and was the father of Martha Nietz (Stoops). He later married Florence Metcalf Nietz. Nietz held several positions prior to his appointment at Pitt including a teacher at Wood County, Ohio, public schools, Superintendent at Maumee, Ohio, and Perrysburg, Ohio, public schools and Dean of the Murphy Collegiate Institute in Sevierville, Tennessee.
His research interests were many and included the history of public education, school administration, international education and old school textbooks. When he retired in 1958, he founded the Nietz Old Textbook Collection by donating his 9,000 volume library of early primary and secondary school texts to the library of the University of Pittsburgh. He had acquired the texts to demonstrate the history of teaching in the early years of the United States. During his career, Dr. Nietz directed or advised over 30 dissertations and master's theses based upon the collection. Dr. Nietz died in 1970.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the papers of John A. Nietz, a professor in the School of Education at the University of Pittsburgh. Much of the collection deals with Nietz' correspondence with students and educators and with the acquisition of the Nietz Old Textbook Collection. In addition there are research files both for his teaching career as well as his scholarly publications. Included is also correspondence about the following organizations, Pennsylvania Association for Adult Education; Pennsylvania State Education Association; Pittsburgh Council on Intercultural Education and Phi Delta Kappa.
Custodial History
The Nietz Papers were housed in the Special Collections department until their transfer to the University Archives in 2013.
Separated Material
Master's Thesis: Development of Public Secondary Education in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania by Edith R. Wilkinson was transferred to University of Pittsburgh Student Manuscripts Collection UA 90.9.22-T
Manuscript: University Extension by C. Stanton Belfour was transferred to the University Archives Personal Files under Belfour, C. Stanton.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of selected textbooks from the 19th Century Schoolbooks Collection are available electronically at http://digital.library.pitt.edu/nietz/.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series:
Series I. Professional Correspondence
Series II. Personal Correspondence
Series III. Book Correspondence
Series IV. Manuscripts, Drafts, Articles, Chapters and Notes
Series V. Research Files
Series VI. Teaching Materials
Series VII. Personal Materials
Series VIII. Photographs
Series IX. Artifacts
University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Syllabi; Photographs; Correspondence; Textbooks -- United States -- Collectors and collecting; John A. Nietz old textbook collection; Education -- United States -- History; Manuscripts (Document genre); Morgan, Gilbert -- Speeches; University of Pittsburgh. School of Education -- Faculty; Nietz, John A. (John Alfred)
- Professional Correspondence, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series features the professional correspondence of John Nietz. Most of these letters deal with teaching at the University, oversight of dissertations, teacher training and evaluations, and job placement for graduates of Pittsburgh as well as other universities. The letters during the war years, 1940-1949, reflect correspondence about studies interrupted by military service.
  - 1922-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5-14)
  - 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 15-24)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
  - 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12-27)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
- Personal Correspondence, II.
  This series contains correspondence that is of a more personal nature to family members and close friends. It is possible that there is some correspondence with people who were personal friends as well as colleagues.
  - 1929-1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Book Correspondence, III.
  This series contains correspondence on the acquisition of the Old Textbook collection. While Nietz had a substantial collection of early text books from 1922-1929, the acquisition activity increases in the 1930's and 1940's and then tapers off in the 1950's.
  - 1931-1939 (Box 3, Folder 21-28)
  - 1940-1945 (Box 3, Folder 29-34)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5-10)
  - 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 11-15)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Manuscripts, Drafts, Articles, Chapters and Notes, IV.
  This series has manuscripts and drafts of various writings that Nietz wrote or shared authorship of. Often files are partial chapters and some remain unidentified.
  - Old Textbooks (Box 4, Folder 19-25)
  - Old Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Old Secondary School Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Evolution of Old Secondary School Textbooks Flyers and Dust Jacket (Box 5, Folder 5a)
  - Textbooks McGuffy Didn't Write (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Old Secondary School Grammar Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - History or Women's Clubs in America (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Adult Education (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - A Gift of Old School Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Beginnings of the Idea of Educational Administration (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Evolution of American School Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Evolution of American Arithmetic Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Early Education in Pittsburgh (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Agricultural Extension Education (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Development of Correspondence Education in the United States (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Methodism on the Headwaters of the Ohio (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Education of Adult Prisoners (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Experiences of a Book Collector (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Development of Reading Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Kingdom of the Mind (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Nietz Old Book Collection (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - History of Reform Jewish Education in America (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - More Students Taking Science and Mathematics (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Schools of Western Europe (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Secondary Education (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Guiding Principles in Teaching the Social Studies (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Development of Physiology Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Europe: Post World War II Education (Box 5, Folder 29-29a)
  - A Philosophy of Education for Pennsylvania (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Education in Pennsylvania (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Good Citizenship Education (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Education and National Defense (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - European Schools (Published Interview) (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - More High School Students Taking Basic Subjects (Criticism) (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Most Popular American Histories (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - University of Pittsburgh Historical Writings (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Includes two essays: "Early Pitt Head an Pioneer in Professional Education" (about Gilbert Morgan), "Origin and Development of the University of Pittsburgh" and a report for the School of Education.
  - History of Education (Box 6, Folder 1-3a)
  - History of Education in Pennsylvania (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Forward Look for Teacher Training Institutions (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - History of Education in the U.S. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Assorted Histories Manuscript Chapters (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Values and Objectives in Teaching Education (partial) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Visual Aids in Teaching Social Studies (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Why Do Textbooks Get Bigger? (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Why the Longevity of the McGuffy Reader? (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Workers' Education (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Evolution of the Teaching of Civil Government in the U.S. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Story of Theater in America (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Student Life in Schools of the Ohio Valley Ninety Years Ago, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Some Findings of Old Textbook Analyses (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Manuscripts on Consumers' Education, Academic Freedom, Language Arts, New England Academies (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Terms in History of Education (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Book Reviews, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 18a)
    Beginnings of Bucknell University; Cultural History of Western Education and Development of Standards in Secondary and Higher Education
  - Nietz Textbook Collection typescript (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - American School Board Journal issues with Nietz Articles, 1921-1930 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Research Files, V.
  Nietz' research interests were varied but include public school administration, history of education in the U.S. and abroad, non traditional education such as correspondence schools or prison education and testing methods. Nietz travelled in Europe and met with ministers of education to collect information about educational systems there. It was difficult to determine Research Files versus Teaching Files in some cases so there will be some overlap between this and the next series, Teaching Files.
  - Research in Adult Education (Box 6, Folder 19-23a)
    Includes Pennsylvania and Pittsburgh
  - Poster of Public Education in the U.S., 1947 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - American Youth Commission (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - California Test Bureau, Aptitude and Other Test Information (Box 6, Folder 26-30)
  - California Test Bureau, Samples of Tests (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - California Test Bureau, Reports and Reviews (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - Cambridge University Booklets, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - C.H. Stoelting Co. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Citizenship (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Civilian Conservation Corps (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Comparative Education (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Courses (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Wesley Barnes Derrick Memorial Booklet (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Early American Textbooks (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Educational Books, 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Educational Test Bureau (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Education and National Defense, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Education in Argentina (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Education in Austria (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Education in Bolivia (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Education in Bulgaria, School Certificate, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Education in Chile (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Education in China, 1935-1955 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Education in Denmark (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Education in Ecuador (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Education in Egypt, 1036-1950 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Education in Estonia, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Education in France (Box 7, Folder 25-26)
  - Education in Germany (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Education in Hungary, Teachers Diploma, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Education in India, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Education in Isarel and Palestine, 1948-1955 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Education in Italy (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Education in Japan, 1943-1956 (Box 7, Folder 32-33)
  - Education in Latin America, 1936-1950 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Education in the Netherlands, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Edcuation in Norway, 1940-1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Education in Panama, 1939-1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Education in Poland, 1921-1947 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Education in Romania, Diploma, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Education in Russia (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Education in Sweden (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Education in Switzerland, 1948-1956 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Education in Taiwan, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Education in Thailand, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Education in Turkey, 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Education in the United Kingdom, 1890-1956 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - History of Education in New York (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Illinios Pamplets, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Educational Serials, 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Aptitude Test Brochures (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Posters, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    United States in Facts and World in Facts.
  - General Electric Company Education and Training Brochures, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Report Cards (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - History of Education Chart, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - History of Education Society Membership Lists, 1962-1968 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Pennsylvania (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
  - Pittsburgh (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Irene Kaufmann Settlement Memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - West Virginia (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - United States (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Mathematics (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Joseph Ray, Mathematician (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Intergroup Relations, Pittsburg Workshop, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - M.A.I.N. Test (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - William Holmes McGuffey (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Drawing and Lettering Excercises (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Teaching Certificates, Maine, 1869, 1874 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Teaching Supplies Advertisments (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Essay: Pay Your Teacher (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Philosophy of Voice (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Flyer, Plumbcreek Normal School, 1874 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Primary Spelling Lessons (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Creative Problem Solving, 1059-1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Parent Teacher Association, 1940-1956 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Reading exams (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Religion and Education (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
  - Educational Research (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Methods of Research in Education (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - School and Society Articles (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - School Life Articles (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - School Work Assignments, 1890, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Sign Language Poster, France and U.S. (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Standardized Monthly Curriculum Tests (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Posters, State Child Labor and Compulsory School Attendance, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Study of Diagnostic and Remedial Procedures in a Reading Clinic Laboratory School, by Marjorie Seddon Johnson (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Test Service Brochures (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Impact of War on Education, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - American Theater (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Menace of the Movies, ca 1930 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Psychological Corporation Test Catalogs, 1956-1960, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Pitt Related Items (Box 9, Folder 31)
    To the Secondary Teacher, Summer Courses for secondary school teachers at Pitt, 1937.
  - Vocabulary and Reading (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Education of Women (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Connellsville Baptist Female Sewing Society Secretary's Book, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Picturesque B & O Railroad Brochure (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - University of Chicago (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - World Book Company Test Brochures (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - William B. Johnson (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Hobby Club of Pittsburgh, Constitution, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - University of London (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, Xi Chapter, University of Pittsburgh, 1926-1932 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Kappa Phi Kappa, 1927-1929 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Books and Booklets on Education Research
    - Education in Panama (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Education in Pennsylvania (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Education in Poland (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Education in Spain (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Education in Sweden (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Education in the Dominican Republic (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Education in the Netherlands (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Education in Turkey (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - International Correspondece Schools (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Jan Amos Komensky (Comenius) (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Moonlight School Study, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - National Home Study Manual and Directory, 1947, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Rhythm Reading (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - The Delineator, a Journal of Fashion, Culture and Fine Arts, January 1894 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Reviews in Educational Forum (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Training, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - United Steelworkers of America training manual, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Westinghouse Electric Company education programs, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Education in Cuba (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Education in Cuba (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Edcuation in India (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Education in Japan (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Education in Norway (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Adult Education (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Workbook with inscription: W.E. Masoner (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Education Journal issues, 1829, 1839 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Curiosities
    This section contains a variety of unusual items related to education.
    - Multiplicatiom Table, 1857 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Paper Currency, 1862-1864 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Aprobation Tokens, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Lancaster County Bank Checks (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Lottery Tickets, 1927-1934 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Reward of Merit (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - E.P. Carpenter Organ Warranty, 1883 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Knitting Instructions (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Elements of Logic by H. Coppee, 1857 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Mary Carlton Nash Mathematics Journals, 1825, 1827 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Thaddeus Stevens Speech Against the Repeal of Public Education, 1835 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Report on Public Instruction in Pennsylvania, by Rev. Gilbert Morgan, 1836 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Guidance Series, KDKA School of the Air, Let's Find a Vocation, October 11, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - New German Text Copies, 1808 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Stamps (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Notes, Bills of Sale, Ribbons, etc, 1800's (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Revolving Interest Table, A.F. Osterloh, 1840 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - I.L. Robison Sales Book, 1860 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Victor Frankel compsition Books, 1922-1923 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Clarke's Cotton Nursery Rhymes (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - English Primer, ca 1800's (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Arithmetic Journal, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Teaching Materials, VI.
  This series includes materials that might have been used for teaching of his classes as well as examples and research from other people.
  - Outlines and Readings (Box 11, Folder 20-27)
  - Examination and Dissertation Materials (Box 11, Folder 28-29)
  - Information on the School of Education and Classes (Box 11, Folder 30-33)
  - Reports, Policies and Data about the School of Education (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - Dissertation Committees (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Comparative Education (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Adult Education (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - History of Education (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Educational Administration (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Vocational Education (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - National Survey of the Education of Teachers form, 1931-1932 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - History of Education (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Eleventh Grade Teaching Units (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Educational Sociology (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Graduate Level Courses and Syllabi (Box 12, Folder 17-18)
  - Examination Forms (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - General Education (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - School of Education Requirements and Guidelines (Box 12, Folder 21-21a)
  - History of Education to 1400 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - History of American Education (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - School of Education Fields and Problems for Investigation, Suggested by Members of the Faculty, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Elementary Chemistry Block Unit Plan, Pittsburgh Public Schools, 1928 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Curricula and Syllabi Developed by Chester A. Buckner
    - Interests and Abilities of Pupils, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Program for Measurements in Secondary Schools, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Curriculum Materials: Planning Areas of Instruction (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Organization of Materials for High School Pupils (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - High School Administration, part 1-2, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 29-30)
    - Extra-Curricular Activities in Secondayr Schools, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 31)
- Personal Materials, VII.
  This series contains some files on various organizations that Nietz belonged to or had some interest in. In addition there are some of his speaking engagements, some materials on his daughter Martha and his composition books from the University of Chicago.
  - Pittsburgh Council on Intercultural Education, 1944-1960 (Box 12, Folder 14-19)
    Minutes, reports and other documents of the organization during Nietz' time as a member.
  - Speaking Engagements (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Membership Cards (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Committee on International Affairs Research (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - World War Two and Misc. (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Bibliography (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Martha Nietz (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Composition Books (Box 18, Folder 1-24)
- Photographs, VIII.
  The photographs are primarily of Nietz' professional and research interests. There is one file of family photos. The file called Assorted Photographs may possibly have family members as well as others.
  - Oversized Photographs of Book Collecting (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Early American Textbooks (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
  - Early Chemistry Textbooks, American (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh School District, Schools Past and Present Exhibit (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Moses Roy (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Nietz Family (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Assorted Photographs (Box 14, Folder 9)
    McGuffy Memorial; Synn Family; Chart of Early Land Titles; Iatoollah a Hooshmail; Unidentifiled Girl; Higher Education in Poland
- Artifacts, IX.
  Over the course of his professional and personal life Nietz collected various artifacts dealing with education. Some items in this series, while interesting, seem unrelated to his interests.
  - Johannes Marzall mathematics journal, 1796 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Mary Kreider Herbarium (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Gulliver's Travels, English Classic Series, no. 60, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Letter: Joseph Ray Family, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - German postcards, bookplates and other (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Excerpt from Concise History of U.S. by John McCulloch, 1797 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Pupil's Homework, ca 1870 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Nicholas Pike to Mr. Price, 1790 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Tuition Payment for John Dalton by Michael Walsh, 1804 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Psalter Leaf, 1210 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Missal Leaf, 1480 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Sheet music, ca 1400 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Arithmetic Excercise Book of Elizabeth Jane McDowell, 1831 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Tabula abcdariae pueriles, title page, 1544 (1549) (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Illuminated text, unknown origin (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Brooks's Reader title page, 1906 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Dictionary page, 1482 (Box 16, Folder 16)